Finding Aid for Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (University of Michigan) publications, 1908-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (University of Michigan) publications 1908-2001, 1960-1998
University of Michigan. Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering.
3 linear feet
9730 Bimu C146 2
Publications produced by or for the Department of Civil and environmental Engineering; includes annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, exhibition catalogs, numerous histories, lecture notes, manuals, newsletters, programs, and reports. Also contains the newsletter from the Civil Engineering Alumni and Friends Association, as well as bulletins and proceedings from the Division of Highway Engineering and Highway Transport.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 1884 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open without restriction
.
[See finding aid for Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (University of Michigan) records.]
The Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering Publications (3 linear foot) includes brochures and pamphlets, exhibition catalogs, numerous histories, lecture notes, manuals, newsletters, programs, and reports. Also contains the newsletter from the Civil Engineering Alumni and Friends Association, as well as bulletins and proceedings from the Division of Highway Engineering and Highway Transport. The publications are organized into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil Engineering. Division of Highway Engineering and Highway Transport.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil and Environmental Engineering.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; Civil engineering alumni and friends association newsletter.; Department of civil and environment engineering newsletter; History of the department of civil engineering
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Civil Engineering. Division of Highway Engineering and Highway Transport.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Exhibition catalogs.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series includes brochures, bulletins, directories, exhibition catalogs, numerous histories, lecture notes, manuals, newsletters, programs, and reports. The only directory in this series is a 1990 sampling of minority alumni of the department. There are a number of histories of the department written from 1908 to 1980. The lecture notes are both from the course Civil Engineering 26 taught by Professor Henry E. Riggs. They are Specifications and Controls published in 1922 and the Engineering Relations: Specifications and Contracts released in 1924. The manual, Laboratory Manual of Bituminous Materials, was issued in 1924.
  The reports include the progress report on the Effects of Forest Clear-Cutting on the Stability of Natural Slopes issued in 1969 and the final report of the Workshop on Construction Engineering Basic Research released in 1982. The Report of the Department of Civil Engineering is a thorough description of the department as it was in 1936. It offers a picture of the structure of the department by specialties and of its laboratories. It also includes courses descriptions, degree requirements for a Bachelor of Science degree, as well as a statement of requirements for advanced degrees. This publication also contains information about the faculty of the department including educational, teaching and professional background, research interests, honors and professional memberships, and a brief list of publications. The volume also includes a sampling of exam questions to assist students of the 1930s in their study of civil engineering.
  - Brochures (Box 1)
    - Graduate Programs in Civil Engineering (Box 1)
    - Environmental Sciences Engineering 1982 (Box 1)
    - Civil Engineering undated, 1958-1996 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Program undated (Box 1)
    - Graduate Studies 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - MLK Day: A Sampling of Minority Alumni, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs
    - Exhibits of the Department of Civil Engineering, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - Bibliography of References in the History of the Department of Civil Engineering (Box 1)
    - Civil Engineering in History at Michigan (Box 1)
    - Department of Civil Engineering Significant Event Timeline 1980 (Box 1)
    - Histories of the Department, 1937, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - History of the Department of Civil Engineering, 1952 (Box 1)
    - History of Civil Engineering at the University of Michigan (Box 1)
    - In History Civil Engineering at Michigan (Box 1)
    - Outline of the History (Box 1)
    - The Department of Civil Engineering from 1950-1970, 1971 (Box 1)
    - The Department of Civil Engineering, 1952 (Box 1)
    - A Short History of Some of the Graduates of the Department, 1908 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Sanitary Experiment Station (Box 1)
  - Lecture Notes
    - Civil Engineering 26: Specifications and Contracts by Henry Riggs (Box 1)
    - Engineering Relations: Specifications and Contracts, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Laboratory Manual of Bituminous Materials, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Alumni Newsletter 1984-1988, 1995, 1997, 2000-2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - ASCE Newsletter 1969 (Box 1)
    - Department Newsletter 1984-1991, 1993-1995, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - InSitu Remediation 1998 (Box 1)
    - The Benchmark 1969 (Box 1)
  - Posters 2002, undated (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - Conference Programs 1987 (Box 1)
    - Robert B. Harris Lecture 1988 (Box 1)
  - Reports (Box 2)
    - Civil Engineering Report, 1949 (Box 2)
    - County Engineers Workshop Reports, 1966-1977, 8 folders (Box 2)
    - Effects of Forest Clear-Cutting on the Stability of Natural Slopes, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Electronic Computers in Engineering Education, First Annual Report, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation of Great Lakes Shore Protection Structures, 1988 (Box 2)
    - 5-Year Review 2000 (Box 2)
    - 5-Year Review Committee Report 2000 (Box 2)
    - North Campus Engineering and Technology Center Plans, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Recycling and Rehabilitating Pavements, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Report on Department of Civil Engineering, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Use of Computers in Engineering Education, Second Annual Report, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Workshop on Construction Engineering Basic Research, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Studies
    - A Computer Program for Leveling Resource Usage by Robert Galbreath, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Analog Computer Fundamentals by Silvio Navarro (Box 3)
    - An Introduction to Digital Computing by Bruce Arden, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Computer Analysis of Structures by Glen Berg, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Effective Distance of Urban Highway Travel for Supermarket Shopping Trips by Clinton Heimbach, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Implications of Time-Sharing Remote-Console Computer Systems by Hadley Smith, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Edition of Engineering Concepts and Perspective, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Waterhammer Analysis of Pipelines by Victor Streeter, 1963 (Box 3)
- Sub Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  - Center for Construction Engineering and Management (Box 3)
  - Division of Highway Engineering and Highway Transport
    - Bulletins
      - Courses in Highway Engineering 1914 (Box 3)
      - Special Announcement of Courses in Highway Engineering and Highway Transport 1916-1917, 1919-1925 (Box 3)
    - Proceedings
      - Annual Conference on Highway Transport 1927-1928 (Box 3)
      - Short Course in Highway Engineering 1915 (Box 3)
    - Programs 1927 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1923-1924, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Materials Laboratory 1979 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Sanitary Engineering Laboratory 1946 (Box 3)
  - Municipal and Highway Laboratory 1913 (Box 3)
  - Outreach, Faculty Activities 1987 (Box 3)
  - Structural Design of Asphalt Pavement Conference 1987 (Box 3)
  - Use of Computers in Education
    - Aeronautical Engineering, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Chemical Engineering, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Electrical Engineering, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Civil Engineering, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Engineering Mechanics, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Geodetic Engineering, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Industrial Engineering, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Materials and Metallurgical Engineering, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Naval Architecture, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Final Report, 1963 (Box 3)